Finding Aid for Theophil Aprill papers, 1914-2000
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Theophil Aprill papers 1914-2000 1990-2000
Aprill, Theophil
1.5 linear feet (in 3 boxes)
2008065 Aa 2
Lifelong member of Zion Lutheran Church, Ann Arbor, Michigan, Aprill served for several years in the 1990s as a member of the Church’s Executive Board. Papers include files relating to the history of Zion Lutheran Church, including a conflict within the church in the mid-1990s.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Material was donated to the library by Theophil and Ruth Aprill (donor no. 9033 ) in November of 2000.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open with the exception of box 3, the Conflict at Zion series, which is closed until November of 2050.
Theophil (Ted) Aprill was born in Ann Arbor and is a life long member of Zion Lutheran Church. He served in the Navy during World War II and upon return from the war received his Bachelor's Degree in Electrical Engineering. He went on to own and operate Allied and A&L Parts, an automotive parts supplier based in Washtenaw County.
Aprill was actively involved in Zion Lutheran Church throughout his life. He ushered at church services for over 35 years and served on numerous Church committees and boards. He served on the Church Life Board and the Worship and Spiritual Life Board in the 1970s, and acted as the chairman of the Centennial Task Force in 1975. He served for several years on both the Executive Board and the Church Council, the latter as Vice President for one year. His service on the Executive Board coincides with a major conflict in the Church, ostensibly centering on the music program, but encompassing larger matters about the style of leadership and worship desired by the congregation, and the fiscal responsibility of the Church.
The Theophil Aprill collection contains two series relating to his activities with Zion Lutheran Church in Ann Arbor, Michigan. These series are Zion History and the Conflict at Zion.
Subjects:
Aprill, Theophil.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Church history.; Lutheran Church--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Zion Lutheran Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
Visual Materials
Construction--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Foresters Camp.; Koch Building and Supply Co.
Genre
Photographs.
- Zion History
  The Zion History series documents Ted Aprill's participation in Zion Lutheran Church and constitutes the bulk of the collection. This contains annual reports, Church bulletins, correspondence, clippings, meeting minutes, sermons, and information on the Zion Retirement Center, a Lutheran Retirement Center in Washtenaw County and associated with the Church. The material in this series is organized chronologically by decade.
  - Aprill, Theophil-Biographical Information (Box 1)
  - 1922-1927 (Box 1)
  - 1942-1949 (Box 1)
  - 1950-1959 (Box 1)
  - 1960-1969 (Box 1)
  - 1970-1979
    - Miscellaneous, 1970-1979 (Box 1)
    - Fred Holtfretter's Call, 1973 (Box 1)
    - Bob Huff, 1973-1978 (Box 1)
    - "To Love and Cherish" Marriage Retreat Materials, 1975 (Box 1)
    - Membership Directories, 1976-1988 (Box 1)
    - Ralph Piper, 1972 (Box 1)
    - Zion Centennial, 1975 (Box 1)
  - 1980-1989 (Box 1)
  - 1990-2000
    - Annual Reports, 1995, 1997, 2000 (Box 1)
    - Aker, Chuck, 1995 (Box 1)
    - Bracklein, Dave, 1996 (Box 1)
    - Church Meeting (on new directions for Zion), 1998 (Box 1)
    - Clippings (Box 1)
    - Cole, Howard, 1992 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1993-1998 (Box 1)
    - Harms, Fred, 1990 (Box 1)
    - Job Descriptions and Organizational Structure, 1990-2000 (Box 1)
    - Johns, Dan, 1990-2000 (Box 1)
    - Membership Directories, 1991-1997 (Box 1)
    - Reorganization/Constitution Review, 1996-1997 (Box 1)
    - Reports, Memos, etc., 1994-1999 (Box 1)
    - Runestad-Rabe, Dana, 1996 (Box 1)
    - Transition Team Materials, 1998 (Box 1)
    - Truscott, Dale, 1996 (Box 1)
  - Photographs - group photo of Foresters Camp (perhaps a University of Michigan group), 1914, and construction site photo, perhaps of an Ann Arbor, Mich. building, 1917 (Box 2)
    Koch Building and Supply Co., Ann Arbor, Mich., was the general contractor of the building under construction.
  - WPAG Live Recording of Zion Church Service, March 8, 1948, 8 phonograph discs; 33 1/3 rpm (Box 2)
- Conflict at Zion
  The Conflict at Zion series contains correspondence, reports, and clippings related to a major conflict that occurred at Zion during the 1990s. Modernization and budgetary needs of the music program and a conflict over the leadership and business style of Pastor Dan Johns were at the heart of this conflict, however the tensions and surrounding these issues affected the congregation as a whole, as well as other administrative aspects of the Church. This conflict ultimately led to a number of congregants and staff members leaving the Church and to a lengthy conflict resolution and reconciliation process.
  [This series is closed until November 2050 ]
  - Clippings, 1996-1997 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence and Notes, 1995-1998 (Box 3)
  - Music Program, 1995-1997 (Box 3)
  - Zion Healing Process, 1996-1998 (Box 3)
Related Material
These papers augment the Bentley Historical Library's rich holdings documenting the religious history of Southeast Michigan. Researchers interested in the history of Ann Arbor's Zion Lutheran Church should also consult the Zion Lutheran Church records, 1833-1981. This collection contains church history, administrative and financial records, and the papers of church organizations and individual papers. The Bentley Historical Library also holds the records of the Lutheran Church in America, Michigan Synod Records and a number of publications related to Zion Lutheran Church.